Guide to the United States Presidents Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
United States presidents collection
1778-1948
GEN MSS 271
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.4
(3 boxes) + 1 portfolio
Letters, legal documents, and other material created or signed by United States presidents.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in portfolio may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to United States Presidents, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Adams, John, 1735-1826; Arthur, Chester Alan, 1829-1886; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Madison, James, 1751-1836; Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869; Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Taylor, Zachary, 1784-1850; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Tyler, John, 1790-1862; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; United States. President
- File List, Series I
  - Adams, John
    - Letters-patent appointing Joseph Hopkinson Indian comissioner for the Oneida Tribe, Philadelphia, 1798 May 4
      Scope and Contents
      Also signed by Timothy Pickering. Accompanied by engraved portrait of Adams. Gift, 1957.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 89
    - Receipt in Adams' hand stating that he has given to William Walters 33 guilders and five stuyvers, Amsterdam, 1781 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Receipt is signed by William Walters. A note on the verso identifies Walters as "a seaman prisoner escaped from England and taken with the Small Pox here at Amsterdam." Gift, 1958.
  - Adams, John Quincy
    - ALS to D[avid] Francis Bacon, Washington, D.C., 1845 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      With envelope.
    - AL (in third person) to Mrs. [Sidney Stotesbury?] Dickerson, 1836 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Removed from: Abraham Lincoln by Nicolay and Hay (New York, 1917). Gift, 1954.
    - ANS to Messers. A Glennie and Son, London, 1817 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Accompanied by small piece of paper: "I John Quincy Adams, of Quincy (County of) Norfolk (and) Commonwealth of Massachusetts."
    - ALS to Henry Wheaton, introducing E. C. Bacon, Washington, D.C., 1844 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Gift, 1927.
    - "Extracts of a Resolution, approved 27 December 1813...23 December 1817 ...23 January 1819...11 January 1822," Department of State, Washington, 1822 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Printed form signed by J. Q. Adams and addressed to Jeremiah Day concerning the depositing of government documents in the libraries of colleges and universities. Address in manuscript.
  - Arthur, Chester Allan. ANS of autobiographical details, [1880 Jun 8] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Gift, 1930.
  - Buchanan, James
    - ANS to the President [James K. Polk?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      With fragment of autograph letter from Joshua Bates. Gift, 1938.
    - ALS to Charles S. Todd, Washington, 1844 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Robert J. Walker, Washington, 1845 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - AL to unidentified recipient, Wheatland near Lancaster, 1852 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Accompanied by a letter from John Bassett Moore to J. H. Penniman, 1924 Jan 26. Gift.
  - Cleveland, Grover
    - 31 ALS, 1 TLS, and 2 telegrams to LeRoy Brooks, 1897-1907 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
      Gift, 1937.
    - ALS to Edward P. Clark, Princeton, 1901 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      With envelope. Gift, 1928.
    - ALS to Robley D. Evans, Princeton, 1899 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      With envelope. Introducing LeRoy Brooks. Gift, 1937.
    - ALS to Joseph O'Connor, Albany, [New York], 1884 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - ALS to Robert M. O'Reilly, Princeton, 1903 Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - ALS to Robert Sedgwick, Princeton, 1905 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      With envelope. Removed from: A Defense of Fishermen by Grover Cleveland (Princeton, 1902). Gift, 1954.
    - ALS to E. Stewart Sumner, Albany, 1884 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Gift, 1956.
    - ALS to William F. Vilas, Chairman, D. P. Bestor, and other members of the Committee of the Democratic National Convention, Albany, 1884 Aug (Box 1, Folder 22)
      This letter, accepting the nomination for President by the Democratic party, was written by Cleveland in the Adirondacks, and sent to Daniel S. Lamont to be copied and transmitted officially to the Democratic party committee. Gift, 1937.
    - Brief for the Supreme Court case of Andrew Spaulding and another versus Albert B. Williams and others, [Buffalo, N.Y.], [1879] (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Autograph manuscript. Accompanied by: typed sheet giving additional facts concerning the case of Spaulding versus Williams, with George A. Bailey's name stamp; ALS from Judge Charles Barker Wheeler to George A. Bailey, Buffalo, 1915 Jun 9; 3 newspaper clippings concerning manuscript briefs of Cleveland. Gift, 1919.
    - Signature, on Executive Mansion stationery, made at Washington shortly after his marriage, 1886 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Gift, 1935.
    - Card from Executive Mansion, Washington, autographed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Card, autographed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Coolidge, Calvin
    - TLS to the Rainbow Division Veterans Association, Washington, 1921 Jun (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Accompanied by 2 TLS from Bentley Mulford to the editor of the Saturday Review and to Andrew Keogh, concerning the letter from Coolidge. Gift, 1925.
    - Holograph letter to William Howard Taft, 1923 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      With a note of transmittal from Taft to Anson Phelps Stokes, on verso, 1927 Apr 12. Gift, 1927.
  - Fillmore, Millard
    - 5 ALS to D[avid] Francis Bacon, Buffalo and Washington., 1843-52 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Accompanied by signature clipped from franked envelope and pasted on sheet of paper.
    - ALS to Messrs. Harper and Brothers, New York, 1846 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      With detailed suggestions for Chauncey Allen Goodrich's edition of Webster's Dictionary, 1847. Purchase, 1955.
  - Grant, Ulysses Simpson
    - Signed photograph, 1866 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Gift, 1928.
    - Warrant for pardon of Richard S. Gray, Washington, 1873 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Accompanied by an etching of Grant. Removed from: Abraham Lincoln by Nicolay and Hay (New York, 1917). Gift, 1954.
  - Harding, Warren Gamaliel
    - TLS to the Rainbow Division Veterans Association, 1921 May (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Gift, 1925.
    - TLS to Dr. W. G. Thompson, Washington, 1922 Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Accompanied by clipping of picture showing Harding using an ax. Gift, 1928.
  - Jackson, Andrew
    - Autograph signature on a land grant to the heirs of James Sufferance, revolutionary soldier, 1832 Jun 13
      Gift, 1934.
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 90
    - Autograph signature cut from printed form, mounted on one sheet, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Forms part of Daggett autograph collection.
    - Closing lines of autograph letter, with signature, Hermitage, Tenn., 1845 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Gift, 1938.
  - Jefferson, Thomas
    - AN in the third person to Edmund M. Blunt, Monticello, 1813 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Thanking him for a copy of the "Nautical Almanac for 1814." Gift, 1935.
    - ALS to Charles Carter, Philadelphia, 1791 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - ALS to Sheldon Clark, Monticello., 1825 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - AN in the third person to Mr. Hatch, 1824 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Inviting him to dine with General Lafayette. Gift, 1933.
    - Address and frank to John Page, esquire, Washington, Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Address and frank to Caesar A. Rodney, Washington, Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Purchase, 1955.
    - ANS to an unidentified recipient, Washington, 1803 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Certificate for grant of land in Ohio, 1802 Apr 1
      Form printed on parchment and filled out in manuscript. Signed by Jefferson as President, James Madison as Secretary of State, and on verso by Henry Dearborn, Secretary of War.
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 91
    - Certificate for grant of land in Ohio, 1806 Jul 16
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 92
    - Certificate for grant of land in Ohio, 1808 Nov 16
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 93
    - Receipt book of the Continental Congress, 1779 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Pages 1049 and 1050, with items receipted by the following persons: John Taylor Griffin, Richard Kenney, Edward Carroll, Thomas Clements, Thomas Jefferson, George Thompson, William Duval, B. Dandridge, John Stratton, John Wilson, William Turner, Robert Anderson and Fortunatus [Tyd--?]. Gift, 1933.
    - Ship's passport issued to Thomas Ward, master of the brig Laura, 1806 Mar 15
      Printed form in two languages, with names and dates supplied in manuscript. Signed by Jefferson and countersigned by Ab. Bishop, Collector of the Customs, New Haven. Gift, 1933.
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 94
  - Lincoln, Abraham
    - ANS to D. T. Jewett, Springfield, [Ill.], 1859 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Signed endorsement of the purpose of the American Union Commission, 1864 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      With picture of Lincoln. Gift, 1928.
  - McKinley, William
    - ALS to John Addison Porter, Executive Mansion, Washington, D.C., 1900 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Gift, 1900.
    - AN written in the third person, Executive Mansion, Washington, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Apparently written by a secretary, accepting an invitation to the twentieth annual dinner of the Yale College Class of 1878.
  - Madison, James
    See also: Box 3, folder 91
    See also: Box 3, folder 92
    See also: Box 3, folder 93
    - "Journal" of the Federal Convention of 1787, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Manuscript copy in the hand of Madison of the "Journal" made by William Jackson as Secretary of the Convention. Gift, 1926.
    - Ship's passport for the schooner Polly, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
      Printed form in English and Dutch, filled out in manuscript. Signed by Madison as Secretary of State and by Henry Daggett, Alderman, for the Corporation of the City of New Haven.
    - Signature on corner cut from an engraved plate, and mounted on sheet of paper (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Pierce, Franklin. Two signatures on small slips, mounted on one sheet, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Polk, James Knox. Closing line of ALS, Washington, 1846 Feb 6 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
    - TLS to Emily Hardy Hall, Washington, D.C., 1942 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      With the last paragraph in manuscript. With envelope.
    - Address of the President, United Nations Flag Day, Washington, D.C., 1942 Jun 14 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      With corrections by FDR. Signed: "For Yale University Library. This is the 1st carbon copy of the original from which I read. Franklin D. Roosevelt." Accompanied by a TLS from Grace G. Tully to Emily Hardy Hall, forwarding the manuscript, 1942 Jun 16.
  - Roosevelt, Theodore
    - TLS (carbon copy) to Governor Frank Swett Black, 1897 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Accompanied by a copy of a letter from William H. Owen to Andrew Keogh, 1930 Jan 9, New York.
    - TL, signed with initials, to Attorney General, [William H. Moody], The White House, Washington, 1906 Jan 16 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      With manuscript corrections and postscript. Gift, 1936.
    - 3 TLS to Dr. W. G. Thompson, 1897-1918 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Accompanied by two pictures of Roosevelt. Gift, 1928.
  - Taft, William Howard
    - AL in the third person to [Henry Beebe] Carrington, Washington, 1910 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      With envelope addressed in an unidentified hand: "Brig. Gen. Henry B. Carrington and Lady." Gift, 1949.
    - 2 TLS to Franklin B. Dexter, 1913, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Gift, 1940.
    - TLS to Henry R. Gruener, New Haven, 1915 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      With envelope. Gift, 1931.
    - 2 typewritten letters to Mr. Keogh, 1916, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      The first letter deals with a gift to the Library of a set of war records; the second acknowledges a clipping. Gift, 1929.
    - TLS to James M. Lamberton, Baguio, Benguet, Philippine Islands, 1903 Apr 18 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - ALS to [John Christopher] Schwab, New Haven, 1914 Jan 7 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      Gift, 1914.
    - Letter to Anson Phelps Stokes, 1927 Apr
      On verso of holograph letter from President Coolidge to Taft.
      See: Box 1, folder 28
    - 3 TLS to W. G. Thompson, 1916-22 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Includes three pictures of Taft. Gift, 1928.
    - 6 ALS to "Miss Mary", 1875 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 66)
      Written while a freshman at Yale. Purchase, 1955.
    - Invitation to a dinner in honor of William Howard Taft, at the Yale Club, 1902 Apr 28 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Taylor, Zachary
    - ALS to William Darius Bishop, Baton Rouge, La., 1848 Oct 22 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Sending his autograph. Gift, 1931.
    - Autograph as President, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
      With autograph of John Middleton Clayton as Secretary of State.
    - Closing lines of a printed military form, 1847 Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Signed by Taylor, Major General, Com'dg.-in-chief. Forms part of Daggett autograph collection.
  - Truman, Harry S. V-E Day Proclamation, 8 May 1945, 1948 Jul 7 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    Photostat inscribed to the Yale University Library and signed by Truman. Accompanied by a TLS from William D. Hassett to Chauncey B. Tinker, 1948 Jul 7. Gift, 1948.
  - Tyler, John. 2 autographs, clipped from letters, mounted on sheet of paper, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Van Buren, Martin
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Saratoga Springs, [18]43 Aug 7 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Autograph on franked envelope addressed to "Miss Mary Mowrie, Washington, D.C.," postmarked Kinderhook, N.Y., Aug 13 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Autograph inscribed "With my respects" on small card, Linderwald, 1948 Apr (Box 2, Folder 75)
      Gift, 1931.
  - Washington, George
    - LS to Gov. George Clinton, White Plains, 1778 Jul 23
      In the hand of his clerk, Tench Tilgham. Accompanied by draft of Clinton's reply, written on wrapper of Washington's letter, 1778 Jul 24, Poughkeepsie. Gift, 1957.
      See: Oversize, box 3, folder 95
    - ALS to Timothy Dwight, Valley Forge, 1778 Mar 18 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      Gift.
    - ALS to Zechariah Lewis, Mount Vernon, 1797 Aug 14 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      Purchase, 1939.
    - ALS to Col. Tho. Marshall, Philadelphia, 1796 Jan 2 (Box 2, Folder 77a)
    - ALS to James Ross, German Town, 1794 Sep 13 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      The paper is watermarked "Washington." Gift, 1932.
    - ALS to Sir John Sinclair, Philadelphia, 1797 Mar 6 (Box 2, Folder 78a)
    - ALS to Brig. Gen. Smallwood, H.Q. Valley Forge, 1778 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      Gift, 1939.
    - ALS to W. S. Smith, Newburgh, 1783 Apr 21 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - ALS to Rev. Ezra Stiles, New Windsor, 1781 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - ALS to John Trumbull, H.Q. Morristown, 1780 Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - ALS to John Trumbull, Mount Vernon, 1799 Jun 25 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      On verso of p. 5 is the following manuscript note: "The Signature of this letter: G. Washington was given to Mr. Cavallo: F. R. S. - July 27th 1801." Gift, 1924.
    - ALS to Jonathan Trumbull, Headquarters, Middle Brook, 1778 Dec 19 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      Endorsed: 19th Decemr 1778, General Washington...recd 6th Janry 1779... He answers Governor Trumbull's objections to the disposition of troops in Connecticut. Gift, 1956.
    - LS to the Congregational Ministers of the City of New Haven, 1789 Oct 17 (Box 2, Folder 85)
      Signature only in Washington's hand.
  - Wilson, Woodrow
    - ALS and TLS to Edward P. Clark, 1888, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - TLS to J. Bentley Mulford, National First Vice-President of the Rainbow Division Veterans, Washington, D.C., 1921 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - TLS to Anson Phelps Stokes, Princeton, 1902 Oct 29 (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Oversize, 1798 May 4
  - Adams, John. Letters-patent appointing Joseph Hopkinson Indian comissioner for the Oneida Tribe, Philadelphia, 1798 May 4 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Jackson, Andrew. Autograph signature on a land grant to the heirs of James Sufferance, revolutionary soldier, 1832 Jun 13 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Jefferson, Thomas
    - Certificate for grant of land in Ohio, 1802 Apr 1 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Certificate for grant of land in Ohio, 1806 Jul 16 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Certificate for grant of land in Ohio, 1808 Nov 16 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Ship's passport issued to Thomas Ward, master of the brig Laura, 1806 Mar 15 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Washington, George. LS to Gov. George Clinton, White Plains, 1778 Jul 23 (Box 3, Folder 95)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 13 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 96)
  - Box 1, folder 23 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 97)